A Finding Aid to the Jan Butterfield Papers, 1950-1997, in the Archives of American Art AAA.buttjan
Archives of American Art
Jan Butterfield papers
1950-1997
AAA.buttjan
Archives of American Art
15 Linear feet
The papers of Jan Butterfield measure 15 linear feet and date from circa 1950 to 1997. Papers contain hundreds of recorded interviews with and lectures by artists, panel discussions of artists and art historians, as well as extensive writings by Butterfield. Also found are project files, personal business records, printed materials, photographs, and additional sound and video recordings related to art subjects.
Butterfield, Jan
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Some of the sound recordings in this collection were digitized during processing and are available for research access at the Archives of American Art offices.
Related Archival Materials note
Also found among the collections of the Archives of American Art is a 1981 panel discussion on Bay area art criticism sponsored by the National Women's Caucus for Art, in which Butterfield participated, as well as an oral history interview Butterfield conducted with Helen Lundeberg for the Archives' Oral History Program in 1980.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Jan Butterfield donated the Robert Irwin material in 1980. Most of the interviews and audio tapes were donated in 1989. An additional 12 feet of papers, including materials previously loaned and microfilmed, and two additional audio tapes,were donated by Butterfield's brother, and Trustee of the Jan Butterfield Trust, Derek Van Alstine in 2002.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 7 series.
Series 1: Interviews and Lectures (Boxes 1-5; 4.2 linear feet)
Series 2: Writings (Boxes 5-7, 16, OV 17; 3.7 linear feet)
Series 3: Project Files (Boxes 8-10, 16; 1.6 linear feet)
Series 4: Personal Business Records (Boxes 10-11, OV 17-19; 1.1 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Materials (Boxes 11-12, 16, OV 17-19; 1.8 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs (Boxes 12-14, 16; 2.2 linear feet)
Series 7: Sound and Video Recordings (Box 15; 0.4 linear feet)
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Jan Butterfield measure 15 linear feet and date from circa 1950 to 1997. Papers contain hundreds of recorded interviews with and lectures by artists, panel discussions of artists and art historians, as well as extensive writings by Butterfield. Also found are project files, personal business records, printed materials, photographs, and additional sound and video recordings related to art subjects.
Interviews and Lectures include hundreds of interviews conducted by Butterfield between 1971 and 1987 with contemporary artists about whom she was writing at the time. The artists Robert Irwin and Sam Francis are represented particularly well. Also found are slide talks, class discussions, and lectures given by artists, which are assumed to have been recorded by Butterfield in most cases. Also among the recordings are recorded performances by John Cage, Joe Goode, Newton and Helen Harrison, Jim Roche, and George Greene. Panel discussions include two notable recordings involving Milton Resnick, one with the painter Edward Dugmore in 1959, and the other with the painter Ad Reinhardt at The Club in 1961, which was later dubbed "The Attack."
The bulk of the writings relate to Butterfield's published work The Art of Light and Space, represented here in multiple drafts, research, and photographs of works of art by the artists discussed in the work including Robert Irwin, James Turrell, Maria Nordman, Douglas Wheeler, Bruce Nauman, Eric Orr, Larry Bell, DeWain Valentine, Susan Kaiser Vogel, and Hap Tivey. Also found are extensive drafts and research for catalog essays for exhibitions of Larry Bell, Richard Shaw, Robert Hudson, and Elmer Bischoff. Drafts of articles and publicity writing are mainly about artists but also some galleries and other art events. There are a few transcripts of recorded interviews, and it appears that many of the writings are based on Butterfield's interviews.
Project files include records relating to Butterfield's involvement with the production of a catalog for the corporate art collection of Pacific Enterprises. These also include additional artist interviews and artist files containing research and writing, mainly by her associate Michael Karp. Also found are photographs and sound recordings for the Waterfront Project at the San Francisco Art Institute, an interdisciplinary community-centered development project that involved Larry Bell, Robert Irwin, Melinda Wortz, Eric Orr, Dr. E. Wortz, Frank Gehry, Newton and Helen Harrison, Josh Young, and students at the Art Institute. And finally, project files include photographs, interviews, and printed material related to publications of Lapis Press, where Butterfield was Executive Director.
Personal business records include correspondence, price lists, financial records, notes, press releases, and career documentation of Butterfield. Printed materials include articles by Butterfield, articles about Butterfield, and articles by Henry Hopkins, most of which are photocopies. There are also clippings, exhibition catalogs, exhibition posters, and publicity. Of note is a disassembled scrapbook pertaining to the controversial Ed Kienholz exhibition at the Los Angeles County Museum of Art in 1966, and a directory of art spaces in Los Angeles from 1978.
Most of the photographs are of works of art by artists about whom Butterfield wrote. Also found are a few files of photographs of artists, some taken by Butterfield, including Philip Guston, Ed Kienholz, Henry Hopkins with Clyfford Still, Robert Irwin, Robert Rauschenberg, and James Turrell. Additional video and sound recordings include artist installations, a documentary on Sam Francis, and an acoustiguide for an Ed Ruscha exhibition.
Biographical/Historical note
Jan Butterfield (1937-2000) was an art writer and critic of contemporary art who spent most of her career in California. She is best known for her writings on late twentieth century installation and craft artists, particularly those who worked in California and the American West.
Butterfield was born Jan Van Alstine in Los Angeles, California in 1937 and attended the Univeristy of California, Los Angeles. She received numerous fellowships and grants from the National Endowment for the Arts as an art critic, and contributed art writing to dozens of exhibition catalogs and art publications including Art International, Images and Issues, Art News, Art in America, and Flash Art. Her most ambitious work of writing was The Art of Light and Space (Abbeville Press: 1993), which profiles the work of contemporary artists Robert Irwin, James Turrell, Maria Nordman, Douglas Wheeler, Bruce Nauman, Eric Orr, Larry Bell, DeWain Valentine, Susan Kaiser Vogel, and Hap Tivey. She was also the author of a 1972 monograph of the Abstract Expressionist painter Sam Francis.
Butterfield held positions in public relations at the Los Angeles County Museum of Art from its opening until 1970, and at the Fort Worth Art Museum from 1970 to 1974. She taught at Northwood Experimental Art Institute in Dallas, Texas, the San Francisco Art Institute, San Jose State University, and Mills College in Oakland, California between 1973 and 1983. At the San Francisco Art Institute, she was Director of the extension program and Coordinator of the visiting artist program and the Waterfront Project between 1976 and 1978. In 1984, Butterfield and the artist Sam Francis co-founded the Lapis Press, where she served as Executive Director from its founding until 1988.
Butterfield was married twice, the second time to Henry Hopkins, Museum Director at LACMA, the Museum of Fine Art of Houston, and the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art. She died in 2000 after an extended illness.
Bell, Larry, 1939-; Bischoff, Elmer, 1916-1991; Cage, John, 1912-1992; Dugmore, Edward, 1915-; Francis, Sam, 1923-1994; Gehry, Frank O., 1929-; Goode, Joe, 1937-; Greene, George; Guston, Philip, 1913-1980; Harrison, Helen Mayer, 1929-; Harrison, Newton, 1932-; Hopkins, Henry, 1928-2009; Hudson, Robert, 1938-; Irwin, Robert, 1928-; Karp, Michael; Kienholz, Edward, 1927-; Lapis Press.; Nauman, Bruce, 1941-; Nordman, Maria; Orr, Eric, 1939-1998; Pacific Enterprises.; Rauschenberg, Robert, 1925-2008; Reinhardt, Ad, 1913-1967; Resnick, Milton, 1917-2004; Roche, Jim; Ruscha, Edward; Shaw, Richard, 1941 Sept. 12-; Still, Clyfford, 1904-1980; Turrell, James; Wheeler, Douglas; Wortz, E.; Wortz, Melinda; Young, R. Joshua; Art critics--California--San Francisco; Art historians--California; Authors--California--San Francisco; Interviews; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sound recordings; Transcripts; Video recordings
- Interviews and Lectures, 1959-1997; Series 1; 4.2 Linear feet Boxes 1-5
  Scope and Contents note
  Recordings in this series are mostly interviews of artists conducted by Butterfield between 1971 and 1987. Also found are slide talks, class discussions, and lectures given by artists, which are assumed to have been recorded by Butterfield in most cases. Artists of the United States who are associated with the Light and Space movement in sculpture are highly represented, as well as artists of the new crafts movement and contemporary West Coast artists in particular. Also among the recordings are recorded performances by John Cage, Joe Goode, Newton and Helen Harrison, Jim Roche, and George Greene.
  Butterfield's interviews were mainly conducted for specific writing projects, either for articles, reviews, published artist interviews, catalog essays, or books Butterfield was writing. Some interviews were conducted over the phone. Some recordings are editing sessions in which Butterfield consults with her subjects during the editing process for a specific article or interview to be published. Multiple, extensive interviews are found with artists Sam Francis and Robert Irwin. A few interviews conducted by others are found, including a radio interview of Henry Hopkins regarding the Clyfford Still bequest to SF Moma, interviews by Henry Hopkins of Joe Goode, Philip Guston (in a recording of a public Q&A), Walter Hopps (with Jan Butterfield), and possibly Milton Resnick, and an interview with Ursula Schneider conducted by Lorri Surrihan. A transcript is found for the interview by Henry Hopkins with Walter Hopps. Additional transcripts, usually highly edited from the recorded version, are found among the published interviews in the Writings series. Most of the lectures found in this series take place in Texas and California, including multiple lectures that took place at the Berkeley Art Museum, the Northwood Experimental Artists Institute in Dallas, Texas, and the San Francisco Art Institute. In all, the series contains 107 sound tape reels, 97 cassettes, and 1 videoreel.
  Panel discussions include two notable recordings that Butterfield seems to have acquired from Milton Resnick during his solo exhibition at the Fort Worth Art Center in 1971. These include a 1959 appearance of Edward Dugmore and Milton Resnick at Southern Illinois State University, and a 1961 debate between Ad Reinhardt and Milton Resnick which later became known as "The Attack," held at "The Club" in New York City. Also found are recordings of a 1976 conference at UCLA entitled "Space and Place" which included talks by Lloyd Hamrol, Richard Serra, Robert Irwin, and others.
  Arrangement note
  Interviews, lectures, and performances are filed in alphabetical order by their subject's name, and multiple recordings for a single subject are filed chronologically under his or her name. Recordings listed in this series are interviews conducted by Jan Butterfield unless otherwise indicated in the folder listing. Often physical tapes contained multiple recordings, and where an additional recording of a different subject is found on a single physical tape, it is noted with the main entry for that tape, and cross referenced under the additional artist's name alphabetically in the item list. Panel discussions are arranged chronologically at the end of the series.
  Additional artist interviews conducted by Michael Karp in the early 1990s are found in the Pacific Enterprises files of series 3, Project files. Additional sound recordings are also found in the Waterfront Project files of series 3, the Lapis Press files of series 3, and in series 7, sound and video recordings.
  - Ansel Adams, 1976 December; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 1)
  - Lita Albuquerque and Richard Misrach interview with unidentified curators at California State University at Fullerton, 1988 July 10; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Item 2)
  - Richard Artschwager, circa 1975; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Item 3)
    First 37 minutes of recording is popular music.
  - Michael Asher, 1979 February 26; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 4)
  - Michael Asher, 1980 August 29; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 5)
  - Michael Asher, 1981 March; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Item 6)
  - Mowry Baden (Box 1)
    See box 5, folder 2; Panel Discussions, Space and Place, UCLA
  - Larry Bell, 1975 April 25; 2 sound tape reels Handwritten note on original box: "Iceberg" (Box 1, Item 7)
  - Larry Bell, 1981 March; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Item 8)
  - Billy Al Bengston, 1976 June 26; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 9)
  - Fletcher Benton, 1980 May; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 10)
  - Joan Brown, 1975 September; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 11)
    Reel also includes circa 43 minute interview with Bruce Conner, October 1974, on side 2 beginning around 46 minutes into tape; also found is a brief fragment of an interview with Paul Karlstrom.
  - Chris Burden, 1974 October; 1 sound tape reels Paper note found with original box. (Box 1, Item 12)
  - Chris Burden, 1974 October; 1 sound tape reels Handwritten notes on original: "telephone conv. re article" and "telephone proofing of tape" (Box 1, Item 13)
  - Chris Burden, Slide Lecture, 1978 December 13; 2 sound tape reels Original labels on reels indicate one side only, but reels are recorded on both sides. (Box 1, Item 14)
    Probably recorded at UCLA
  - Daniel Buren Lecture, "Space as Support," Berkeley, Calif., 1979 January 18; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 15)
  - John Cage Performance of "Empty Words" and Lecture, San Francisco Art Institute, 1978 October; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 16)
    Taped over an undated recording of a Waterfront Project meeting (see Series 3: Project files); a fragment of the earlier recording is found in the last minute of side 1 and all of side 2 of the reel.
  - Vita Celmins, 1980 February 20; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 17)
  - Judy Chicago, 1978 July; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 18)
  - Judy Chicago, circa 1979; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 19)
  - Judy Chicago, undated (Box 1)
    See box 2, item 13; David Hockney interview, 1978
  - Christo, 1971 June; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Item 20)
  - Robert Colescott, 1979 February 1; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 21)
    Reel begins with a 70 minute fragment of a circa 1977 interview with Robert Irwin.
    Original label on reel reads "Josh Young, tape #2, side 1," but there is no recording on Josh Young on the reel.
  - Bruce Connor, 1974 October (Box 1)
    See box 1, item 11; Joan Brown interview
  - Ron Cooper, 1980 December 14; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 22)
  - Leonard Cutrow, 1985 October 11; 1 Sound cassettes Handwritten note on original cassette: "Life" (Box 1, Item 23)
  - Leonard Cutrow, Interview by unidentified male interviewer, circa 1990-1992; 1 Sound cassettes (microcassette) (Box 1, Item 24)
  - Ron Davis, circa 1976; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 25)
  - Laddie John Dill, undated (Box 1)
    See box 4, item 18; Hap Tivey, Interdisciplinary Seminar and Interview, San Francisco Art Institute, 1977 October
  - John Dowell, 1979 June; 1 sound tape reels Handwritten note on original: "Telephone conversation for article" (Box 1, Item 26)
  - Edward Dugmore (Box 1)
    See box 5, folder 1; Panel Discussions, The Influence of Modern Painting on Our Tradition
  - Tom Eatherton, 1980 December 14; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 27)
  - Sam Francis, 1979 June 26; 2 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 28)
    Although reel 1 of 2 is dated Summer 1979 and reel 2 is dated 6/26/79, they are clearly from the same interview.
  - Sam Francis, 1979 September 9; 1 sound tape reels Handwritten notes on original box: "Pier 46" and "Last catalogue tape / some good info - scattered through" (Box 1, Item 29)
  - Sam Francis, 1979 November 29; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 30)
  - Sam Francis, 1979 December; 1 Sound cassettes Duplicate of sound tape reel; Handwritten note on cassette: "Also on reel-to-reel"; 2 Sound cassettes Original; 1 sound tape reels Original (Box 1, Item 31)
    Sequence of original recordings unclear, but appears to be cassette marked "afternoon tape" first, cassette marked "eve one" second, and reel marked "tape at house" third.
  - Sam Francis, circa 1979; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 32)
    Handwritten note on original reel reads "Manuel Neri - Joan Brown over discussion of later tape," but Neri and Brown are not present on the tape.
  - Sam Francis, circa 1979; 1 Sound cassettes Sound quality is very poor. Handwritten note on original cassette: "Pier 46 (Garner Tullis w/ Sam)" (Box 1, Item 33)
  - Sam Francis, 1980 January 18; 1 Sound cassettes Handwritten note on original cassette: "Final corrected manuscript discussion" (Box 1, Item 34)
  - Sam Francis, Flash Art interviews, 1981 November; 3 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Item 35)
    Sequence of original cassettes is unclear.
  - Sam Francis, Editorial review of Flash Art interview, 1981 November; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Item 36)
  - Sam Francis, Francis and Butterfield testing stereo equipment, undated; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Item 37)
  - Helen Frankenthaler Lecture, Northwood Experimental Art Institute, Dallas, Tex., 1973 March; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Item 38)
  - Joe Goode, Interview conducted by Henry Hopkins, 1972 December 21; 1 Sound cassettes Tape is unlabeled. (Box 1, Item 39)
    Tape also contains poor quality recording of a group discussion with unidentified participants
  - Joe Goode, Performance and Interview, 1973 Janaury; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 2, Item 1)
    Contains a 13 minute performance followed by an interview with the artist.
  - Joe Goode, 1975 August; 1 sound tape reels (Box 2, Item 2)
  - Joe Goode, 1981 November; 2 Sound cassettes Handwritten note on original cassette 1 of 2: "Arco Catalog" (Box 2, Item 3)
  - Bob Graham, 1979 February 26; 1 sound tape reels (Box 2, Item 4)
  - George Greene, 1973; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 2, Item 5)
  - Philip Guston, 1979 January 6; 1 sound tape reels (Box 2, Item 6)
  - Philip Guston, 1980 February 13; 1 sound tape reels Handwritten on original box: "Approval of article for Images and Issues" (Box 2, Item 7)
  - Philip Guston, Question and Answer with Henry Hopkins, San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, 1980; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 2, Item 8)
    Taped for the documentary on Guston entitled "A Life Lived," during Guston's 1980 retrospective at SFMOMA.
  - Lloyd Hamrol (Box 2)
    See box 5, folder 2, Panel Discussions, Space and Place, UCLA
  - Newton and Helen Harrison, Performance, Lecture, and Interview at San Francisco Art Institute, 1977 February 17; 1 sound tape reels Handwritten on original box: "In 'Meditations' show SFAI / Performance and partial interview" (Box 2, Item 9)
    Interview begins approximately 10 minutes into side 2. Tape also contains a fragment of an interview with an unidentified male sculptor, circa 1975, beginning approximately 76 minutes into side 2.
  - Newton and Helen Harrison, 1978 June 28; 1 sound tape reels (Box 2, Item 10)
  - George Herms, 1975 January 31; 1 sound tape reels Handwritten on original box: "San Jose State exhib" (Box 2, Item 11)
  - David Hockney Lecture, San Francisco Art Institute, 1978 November 3; 2 sound tape reels (Box 2, Item 12)
  - David Hockney, 1978 December 5; 2 sound tape reels (Box 2, Item 13)
    Also contains fragments of two earlier recordings, including an undated recording of a Waterfront Project meeting (see Series 3: Project files) on side 2 of reel 1, and an undated interview with Judy Chicago, 22 minutes into reel 2.
  - Henry Hopkins for the "Artscene" radio series about the Clyfford Still Exhibition at San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, circa 1975; 1 sound tape reels Additional label on original box: "from Eleanor Dickinson" with residential address (Box 2, Item 14)
    Broadcast by KPFK in Los Angeles, Calif.
  - Walter Hopps Interviewed by Henry Hopkins and Jan Butterfield, 1976 June 3; 5 sound tape reels Includes transcript (Box 2, Item 15)
    Conducted in conjunction with the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art exhibition, "Painting and Sculpture in California: The Modern Era"
  - Robert Hudson, circa 1976; 1 sound tape reels (Box 2, Item 16)
  - Robert Hudson, 1976 July; 1 sound tape reels (Box 2, Item 17)
  - Robert Irwin, Lecture and Interview, Texas Christian University, 1971 April; 1 Sound cassettes Duplicate of cassette 1 of 3; 3 Sound cassettes Originals; cassette 1 is labeled sides A and B, cassette 2 is labeled C, and cassette 3 is labeled D; all cassettes are mis-labeled 1972.; Original cassette 1 of 3 exists in the form of 2 duplicate tapes made by the creator; original recording is not in the collection. (Box 2, Item 18)
    Lecture found on cassettes 1 and 2; interview begins in the last 15 minutes of cassette 2 of 3, side 2.
  - Robert Irwin, San Diego, 1972; 1 Sound cassettes Duplicate of cassette 1 of 2; 2 Sound cassettes Originals; cassette 1 of 2 labeled sides E and F and "interview;" cassette 2 of 2 labeled "Sequence of events - Personal" (Box 2, Item 19)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
    Original tapes in poor condition; use existing duplicate for access.
  - Robert Irwin, Lecture, Art Center Fort Worth, circa 1972; 1 Sound cassettes Original; labeled sides G and H.; 1 Sound cassettes Duplicate; Sound distorted (Box 2, Item 20)
    Original cassette is damaged; use existing duplicate for access.
  - Robert Irwin, circa 1972; 2 Sound cassettes Originals; cassettes labeled sides I and J, and "preliminary interview, article #3"; 2 Sound cassettes Duplicates (Box 2, Item 21)
    Interview begins on cassette 1, on side labeled "I," and continues on cassette 2, on the unlabeled side. Side labeled "J" contains unrelated recording of an Art Center staff party with Robert Irwin present.
    Copy of interview begins on duplicate cassette 1, side labeled "I," and continues on duplicate cassette 2, which is labeled "second 1/2."
    Original cassettes are damaged; use duplicate cassettes for access.
  - Robert Irwin, Lecture, California State University, Humboldt, 1973 February 28; 1 Sound cassettes Duplicate of sound from original video reel; 1 Videoreels (½ inch) (Box 2, Item 22)
  - Robert Irwin, Social Gathering, San Francisco, 1973 March; 1 Sound cassettes Original, not dated; labeled "At Nell's House"; 1 Sound cassettes Duplicate; labeled "At Nell's House" (Box 3, Item 1)
    Original cassette is damaged; use duplicate cassette for access.
  - Robert Irwin, Los Angeles, 1974 July; 1 sound tape reels Box labeled "Personal interview, Los Angeles, New material for book, parts 3-4 (I have part 1 in long hand)" (Box 3, Item 2)
    Recording on side 1; May 30, 1975 interview on opposite side of same reel
  - Robert Irwin, 1975 May 30; 1 sound tape reels Box label reads "Teleph. conv. re: Chicago & Fort Worth" (Box 3, Item 3)
    Recording on side 2; July 1974 interview is on opposite side of same reel.